Guide to the William Wallace Booth Papers, 1922-1973 AIS.1973.23
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Oakland Corporation, 1961-1966; 2.
  - Subject Files, 1961-1964; V.
    - United States Steel Proposal, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 250)
      Memorandum of understanding (marked confidential draft) between US Steel (USS) and Oakland Corporation in regard to US Steel will provide financial assistance for the construction of Building No. 1 and have priority rights not only in building no. 1, but also in subsequent development by the Oakland Corporation in the Oakland area. Transmitted to US Steel by a letter of transmittal, February 20, 1964. Correspondence, March 5, 1964 - To US Steel, in regards to that Oakland Corporation has no objections to the participation of several companies in the project. Memo, March 6, 1964 - To all members of the B/D in regards to decisions to be made at the next board meeting in regards to that USS desires to have the project be made a civic project with at least five companies participating; and in regards to a decision on whether or not to go ahead with the purchase of land for the first building. Note: concern over the first question centered around the delay by the availability of outside financing which would expedite construction. Memo, March 18, 1964 - To Booth in regards to the March 11 board meeting at which details of entering a joint project with USS were discussed, also there was a discussion of land acquisition for the first phase of the project and a resolution to enter a joint venture with USS and others. Enclosure: A report of the March 11, board meeting containing an outline of 1. the proposal from USS; 2. Oakland Corporation's responsibilities; 3. cost of land acquisition; and 4. recommended action by the board.
    - News Releases, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 251)
      National release: Date line Pittsburgh, April, 1962 announcing the formation and future plans of Oakland Corporation. Dateline, November 27, (1962?), announcement of the appointment of Fred Smith as Oakland Corporation president.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 9, Folder 252)
      - Pittsburgh Regional Planning Association plan for Oakland (Pittsburgh Press, William Allan, reporter) includes map of projected plans, November 21, 1961; 1.
      - Oakland projects at a glance - an outline summary (Pittsburgh Post-Gazette) Also an article on the Planning Association plans (Mel Seidenberg, reporter), November 21, 1961; 2.
      - Editorials from the city's two daily newspaper supporting the planning association's idea, November 22, 1961; 3.
      - Analysis of the planning association's plans, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, November 25, 1961; 4.
      - John E. Williams, county commander of the American Legion protest against the planning association's proposal, especially the idea to put a parking garage under the front lawn of Soldiers and Sailor's Hall, November 27, 1961; 5.
      - Noting a riff between the Regional Industrial Development Corporation (RIDC) and the Greater Pittsburgh Chamber of Commerce over which organization should be responsible for redevelopment in the Pittsburgh area, November 29, 1961; 6.
      - Front page announcement of Oakland Corporation's Panther Hollow project (Pittsburgh Post-Gazette), Herbert G. Stein, reporter) Also, under the same dateline, a front announcement in the Pittsburgh Press, (William Allan, reporter), March 31, 1962; 7.
      - New York Times article announcing Oakland Corporation's Plans, April 1, 1962; 8.
      - Analysis of Oakland Corporation's proposal. (Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, Herbert Stein), April 2, 1962; 9.
      - Pittsburgh Post-Gazette editorial endorsing the Oakland Corporation's proposal, April 3, 1962; 10.
      - Mayor Barr takes first action in seeking funds for urban renewal in Oakland. Review of Oakland Corporation's plans. (Pittsburgh Press, Ralph Bre, reporter), July 1, 1962; 11.
      - Article from Chemical Week on the development and function of research parks, July 15, 1963; 12.
      - In regards to the refusal of the DePasqual to sell property to Oakland Corporation It claimed the corporation would not be able to develop the land and pointed to the fact that USS had still not committed itself, (The Pitt News), April 29, 1964; 13.
      - Fred smith resigns as Oakland Corporation president (Pittsburgh Press & Pittsburgh Post-Gazette), November 5, 1964; 14.
      - Undated articles - in regards to desire by residents to keep Pitt from taking Oakland over. This concerned the Planning Association desire to a research park in the Upper Hill. Oakland Corporation names its board of directors Oakland Corporation still seeking a president; in regards to Park H. Martin did not want the Job, 15.
- Aspen Corporation, 1965-1968; 3.
  The Aspen Corporation was a business formed circa 1966 by Booth and others. Aspen's primary purpose was to sell searches of legal materials that had been recorded on magnetic tape as part of a computerized library. Its secondary purpose was to help clients create and search their own computerized legal library.
  Materials within the Aspen Corporation subgroup include: correspondence, financial records, memoranda, minutes, organizational and foundational documents, and reports.
  - Organization and Purpose, October 27, 1966; I.
    - Aspen Corporation Goals and Plans (Box 9, Folder 252A)
      Includes: introduction, Plan of Operation, suggested specific recording plans, plans for developing a marketing organization
  - Minutes, 1965-1968; II.
    - 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 253)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1968; III.
    - 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 254)
      - In regards to appointment of a chairman of the ad hoc committee of the university trustees to meet with John Horty concerning organization of the AC, July 9, 1965; 1.
      - From AC President Horty to Gwilym Price, university board chairman in regards to a proposal to sell the university 50% (1000 shares) of AC stock through the, yet to be organized, non-profit Merlin Foundation. (Note: the function of the proposed foundation is set forth in this letter), August 3, 1965; 2.
      - Letter from the Legal Research Foundation, Inc. offering to AC the right to publish the "Automated Statutory Reporter and Statutes in Point", February 1, 1966; 3.
      - In regards to the suggested agreement between AC and the Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc., February 22, 1966; 4.
      - Legal questions in regards to the contract between AC and the Dept. of HEW and the proposed subcontract between HEW and the university, July 25, 1966; 5.
      - A brier note that Time, Inc. may be interested in working out a deal with AC, December 2, 1966; 6.
      - Letter from Philips Appel & Walden, New York stock brokers, agreeing in principal to underwrite the issue of AC stock provided certain conditions listed in the letter are met, December 20, 1967; 7.
      - Letter from William Wallace Booth submitting his resignation as a member of AC board, March 12, 1968; 8.
  - Memoranda, 1965-1967; IV.
    - 1965-1967 (Box 9, Folder 255)
      - Setting forth the understanding whereby the university would transfer to AC all the tapes and tapes in progress programmed to provide service on legal points in exchange for 1000 shares of AC stock. The memo also alludes to a foundation which may be formed to be the university's agent, July 20, 1965; 1.
      - Evaluation of the AC process from attorneys who used the service; also a list of the searches purchased since June 1, 1965, September 28, 1965; 2.
      - Summary of planned promotional activities designed to acquaint attorneys in Allegheny County with the Automated Law Service, September 28, 1965; 3.
      - In regards to a $1 million loan from Times Mirror to complete the computerizing of state statutes; and an additional $1.5 million to construct industry files and for general and administrative expense, November 21, 1966; 4.
      - In regards to provisions of the Times Mirror proposal to AC, December 5, 1966; 5.
      - Enumeration of companies with whom AC has negotiated in an effort to obtain working capital, November 29, 1967; 6.
      - From Edison Montgomery to the university chancellor recommending that the university divorce itself from AC. Reason, AC was accumulating a deficit without any prospect of making a profit, December 11, 1967; 7.
  - Financial Statements, 1965-1966; V.
    - 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 256)
  - Subject Files, 1965-1968; VI.
    - Aspen Corporation/Aspen Systems Corporation, 1.
      - Agreement, January 16, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 257)
        Agreement between the university and AC whereby the university assigned to AC all rights and duties it held under a lease from Webster Hall. In effect, provided AC with office and production space and equipment.
      - Marketing (Box 9, Folder 258)
        Marketing Program, "A Proposed Marketing Program for Automated Law Search," prepared for AC by Clinton Advertising, Inc., undated in regards to a sales program designed to acquaint the legal profession with the ALS process; thus expanding AC's market.
      - Prospectus, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 259)
        Prepared by Philips Appel and Waden.
      - Description of the use of the Automatic Law Search (ALS) (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - The Merlin Foundation, 2.
      - 1965 (Box 9, Folder 261)
        - By-laws, 1.
        - Proposal for University Participation in Aspen Corporation, 2.
        - Letter of transmittal to the University Secretary, Stanton C. Crawford from John F. Horty, AC Director. Enclosure: A suggested draft of a resolution by the Executive Committee of the university board authorizing the transfer of magnetic tapes, which had been processed by the university, in exchange of 50% of AC stock, August 6, 1965; 3.
        - Letter of transmittal to Acting Chancellor Crawford. Enclosure: transfer agreement in regards to the university's agreement to transfer certain assets to the Merlin Foundation (MF), August 26, 1965; 4.
        - Minutes of the First MF meeting. Attachments: resolution transferring certain MF assets to the AC in exchanges for 1000 shares of AC stock; Attach. List A, assets transferred by the University to the MF then from MF to AC. Attach. Agreement between Horty and MF whereby Merlin agreed not to sell its interest in AC to an outside party without first giving Horty 60 day option to buy the shares back; Horty agreed not to take part in any similar Corporation for five years and give MF a 60 day option if he wished to sell his share, September 14, 1965; 5.
        - Lease and agreement between the University and AC to be executed simultaneously with the transfer of assets from AC to MF, September 14, 1965; 6.
    - Times Mirror, 3.
      - 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 262)
        - Report on the growth of the LA Times, 1.
        - Report to T-M stockholders, June 1966; 2.
        - Interim report, November 1966; 3.
        - T-M Annual Report, 1965; 4.